{
  "reference_number": "9095",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We cannot delay on achieving net zero emissions till the second half the century."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Whilst the likes of methane is in the environment for a much shorter period of time it's impact on the environment is much greater\n\n therefore we need to work on zero emissions by 2050 and zero impact on the environment. I actually believe we should aim for\n below zero carbon emissions by 2050 if it is achievable so that we have a positive impact on the environment. I'm thinking what more\n\n we can do globally."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need to be able to standalone on this and not pass the buck to other countries. We should encourage other countries to look at\n doing the same."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only if we can do better than our target of zero carbon emissions. We need to be ambitious because the future of the world\n depends on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Sorry but I do not understand the question that is being asked so I cannot answer"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "I say yes reluctantly as I would very much like for this country to meet the targets set. I think what is important is that we have all\n\n parties on the same wavelength and working together so that any transition or change of government does not affect the plans that\n are already in place. This should have the involvement of all parties at all times so that a new government does not come into power\n and is clueless to the plans on achieving zero emissions by 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only under exceptional circumstances as stated in the question. We should always being heading in the right direction i.e.\n\nalways reducing our emissions even if we are slightly behind the target. In such circumstances I would hope that it is not a significant\nadjustment. If the adjustment is considered significant then there should be a full review as to why we have fallen behind in our\ntargets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that all the considerations mentioned on page 44 to be relevant. If there are found to be considerations missing then they\n\nshould be added immediately."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I imagine the Climate Change Commission will advise the government of the timeframe it has and that it will provide support and\n\nexpertise on setting out these plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I do not have anything to add here that has not already been mentioned on page 44."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It should do more than advise and monitor. It should also be part of the decision making."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "In the past the National government has failed in its duty to implement good policy and practice in regards to NZ ETS."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The UK Committee model sounds good. As stated our Commission should have similar credibility and transparency."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely yes!!! Currently the world is reacting instead of adapting."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Having good measurement tools and models is important so that we have accurate data to respond to and have confidence in our\n\nplan. Thank you for allowing me to submit my thoughts."
    }
  ]
}
